<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                         <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../docbook/xinclude.mod" >
                         %xinclude;
                         <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
<!--the document properties were transferred to "dockbook/dbgenent.mod"-->
                         ]>
<section id="rdf" role="normative | informative">
  <title>DMLex RDF serialization</title>

  <section>
      <title>Design principles</title>
      <para>The RDF serialization used in this document follows the following principles</para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The RDF serialization uses an vocabulary defined at the namespace <code>https://www.oasis-open.org/to-be-confirmed/dmlex</code>, al elements of the vocabulary are in this namespace</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The vocabulary file provides RDF Schema and OWL axioms which implement the restrictions described by the data model. It also provides a linking to the <ulink url="https://www.w3.org/2016/05/ontolex/">OntoLex-Lemon</ulink> model. The ontology provides rules to infer an OntoLex-lemon model from DMLex data. This is achieved by means of subclass and subproperty axioms and so conversion can be performed by an OWL reasoner.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>All elements of the modules are modelled as individuals with an appropriate class definitions</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>Each other object type is associated with a property (with a lowercase initial letter) and a class (with an uppercase initial letter. In all case the range of this property is the class</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>Arity of properties is implemented by means of OWL class restrictions.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>Listing order can be specified with the property <code>dmlex:listingOrder</code> with values starting from 1 and ascending</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
              <para>The implementation is not aware of which modules are in use, to enable publishing on the web. As such cardinality constraints that are only required in a module are not implemented.</para>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>DMLex RDF serialization elements</title>
  <xi:include href="elements/LexicographicResource.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="elements/Entry.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="elements/PartOfSpeech.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  </section>
 

</section>

