<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbook/docbookx.dtd" >
<article status="Working Draft 01" lang="en-US">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Data Model for Lexicography (DMLex), Version 1.0</title>
  </articleinfo>
  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>What kind of data model this is</title>
      <para>
        This is a data model in the most abstract sense.
        It does not presuppose any particular implementation or serialization.
        The data model is formulated here in terms of objects, attributes of objects, relationships between objects,
        and attributes of relationships. How these things translate into things in specific implementations,
        such as database table rows or XML elements, is a question the data model is agnostic about.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each object, attribute and relation in this data model is of a certain data type.
        The data type of an object or relation determines which attributes it may or must have,
        and which objects it may or must be related to.
        The data types in this data model have names such as entry, headword, sense.
      </para>
      <para>
        One very common relation between objects in lexicography is the parent-child relation.
        The organization of lexicographic objects such as entries, headwords and senses into
        hierarchical trees of parents and children has been a pervasive design pattern in lexicography
        since digitization began. Consequently, in this data model, the parent-child relation is also very prominent.
        Many data types in this specification are defined in terms of the (types of) parents and children their instances can have.
      </para>
      <para>
        On the other hand, parent-child relations are not the only type of relation that appears in this data model.
        Parent-child hierarchies are only used here to model the basic entry-headword-sense skeleton of a dictionary.
        Other phenomena, such as cross-references between entries, or the inclusion of senses under other senses as subsenses,
        are modelled here with other types of relations, relations which connect entries to other entries,
        senses to other senses. These other relations can be said to "break out" of the traditional tree-like
        hierarchy of a dictionary, and to "annotate" the basic parent-child skeleton with additional information.
      </para>
      <para>
        The basic tree-like hierarchy of a dictionary is defined in the core of this specification (in the next section after this),
        while additional functionality, which sometimes breaks out of the tree-structured pattern, is defined in additional modules.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Relationship between the core and the modules</title>
      <para>
        The core specification of DMLex gives you all the data types you need in order to data-model
        a basic, simple lexicographic resource (a dictionary).
        According to the core specification, a lexicographic resource contains one or more entries,
        and each entry is an easily processable tree structure with
        headwords, senses, definitions, example sentences and so on.
      </para>
      <para>
        The core specification is deliberately designed to be basic and skeletal.
        It is an inventory of data types which you can use to model a very simple lexicographic resource.
        The core can be extended with modules.
        Each module brings in additional data types and/or adds extra attributes
        into data types found in the core specification (or in other modules).
      </para>
      <para>
        The following things are not covered by the core specification, and are handled in the modules instead.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The core specification is a data model for monolingual dictionaries only.
            If you wish to data-model a bilingual dictionary, you need to bring in the translation module.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The core specification has no data type for modelling dictionaries of collocations,
            or for including collocation information in dictionaries
            (that is, information about how the headword usually occurs with other words).
            To include such information in a dictionary you need to bring in the collocation module.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The core specification has no data categories for attaching pragmatic labels to entries, senses or examples:
            labels such as "vulgar", "colloquial", "regional" and so on.
            To include such information in your dictionary you need to use the labelling module.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The core specification makes no provision for cross-referencing between entries and senses,
            for modelling sense relations such as synonymy or antonymy. For that you need the linking module.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The core specification does not make it possible to add variant forms to lexical items
            (i.e. the words described by the lexical resource), such as spelling variants.
            In DMLex, such things are considered to be a special case of linking, and you need the linking module for that.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the core specification, the senses of an entry are a flat (non-hierarchical) list.
            The core specification makes no provisions for organizing the senses of an entry
            into a hierarchical list of senses and subsenses, or for including subentries inside entries.
            In DMLex, such things are considered to be a special case of linking, and you need the linking module for that.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the core specification, information such as headwords, their parts of speech and their inflected forms
            have entry-wide scope (they apply to the whole entry)
            while information such as definitions and examples have sense-wide scope (they apply only to one sense).
            There is no way in the core specification to declare that, for example,
            a headword has one plural form in one sense and another plural form in another sense.
            To do such things you need to bring in the scoping module.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

</section>
  <section id="core">
    <title>Core</title>

    <section>
      <title>Tree structure</title>
      <para>Legend:</para>
      <simplelist type="vert">
        <member>1 = one</member>
        <member>+ = one or more</member>
        <member>? = zero or one</member>
        <member>* = zero or more</member>
      </simplelist>
      <programlisting format="linespecific">
- lexicographicResource
   - entry +
      - headword 1
      - pronunciation *
      - partOfSpeech *
      - inflectedForm *
      - sense *
         - senseIndicator ?
         - definition ?
         - example *
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        The cardinalities indicated by these symbols in the diagram are informative, and are explained in more detail below.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>lexicographicResource</title>
      <para>
        A lexicographic resource is... (another word for dictionary?)
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>name, authors, publisher, URL... TBD</listitem>
        <listitem>language, any translation languages: TBD</listitem>
        <listitem>controlled vocabularies, external authorities: TBD</listitem>
        <listitem>notation(s) used for pronunciation transcriptions: TBD</listitem>
        <listitem>ID policy: are the IDs of entries and senses given explicitly, or are they computable from other data, and how (eg. headword + pos)?</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>One or more of entry.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The order of entries inside a lexicographic resource is not significant.
        If the reader agent wishes to order the entries, it is allowed to show them to the end-user in any order,
        perhaps using hints given in the the entries (headword, listing order) and in the lexicographic resource (language).
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>entry</title>
      <para>An entry is a part of a lexicographic resource which contains information related to exactly one headword.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>dictionary</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>id: required or computable</listitem>
        <listitem>listingOrder: optional</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>one headword</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or more partOfSpeech</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or more inflectedForm</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or more sense</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Note: it is valid for an entry to contain only a headword and nothing else.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>headword</title>
      <para>A headword is the main organising element of an entry within a lexicographic resource.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>entry</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Guidance: Can the headword be a multiword thing? Yes.</para>
      <para>Guidance: How do you model headword variants? Use the linking module instead.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>pronunciation</title>
      <para>It is... TBD</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent - one of:</title>
        <listitem>entry</listitem>
        <listitem>headwordTranslation (from the translation module)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes (at least one)</title>
        <listitem>transcription: optional; the notation (IPA or other) is specified in the lexicographic resource's metadata</listitem>
        <listitem>soundfile: optional: non-empty string, path orURL </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>partOfSpeech</title>
      <para>Any of the word classes to which a lexical item may be assigned, e.g. noun, verb, adjective, etc.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent - one of:</title>
        <listitem>entry</listitem>
        <listitem>headwordTranslation (from the translation module)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>value: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>inflectedForm</title>
      <para>An inflected form is a form of the inflectional paradigm of the headword.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent - one of:</title>
        <listitem>entry</listitem>
        <listitem>headwordTranslation (from the translation module)</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>indicator: optional, e.g. "plural", reference to a controlled vocabulary</listitem>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>sense</title>
      <para>A sense is a part of an entry which groups together information relating to a meaning of the entry's headword, for example definitions, examples and translations.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>entry</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>id; required or computable</listitem>
        <listitem>listingOrder: required or implicit</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children (at least one)</title>
        <listitem>zero or one of senseIndicator</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or one of definition</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or one of headwordTranslation (from the translation module)</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or one of example</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>senseIndicator</title>
      <para>A senseIndicator is a short statement that indicates the meaning of a sense and permits its differentiation from other senses in the entry.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>sense</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>definition</title>
      <para>A definition is a long statement that describes and or explains the meaning of a sense.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>sense</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Guidance: What is the difference between a sense indicator and a definition?</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>example</title>
      <para>An example is an instance of a lexical item's usage in a specific sense.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>sense</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para/>
    </section>

</section>
  <section id="module-translation">
    <title>Translation module</title>
    <para>
      The translation module adds the data types headwordTranslation and exampleTranslation
      as optional children of sense and example from the core specification.
    </para>
    <para>
      Additionally, the translation module adds a few attributes to the core's dictionary data type,
      to indicate the language or languages in which the translations are. TBD.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>headwordTranslation</title>
      <para>Tells us the translation equivalent of the headword in one of its senses.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>sense</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>language: required or implicit, reference to a controlled vocabulary</listitem>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>zero or more partOfSpeech</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or more pronunciation</listitem>
        <listitem>zero or more inflectedForm</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>exampleTranslation</title>
      <para>Tells us the translation of an example.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Parent</title>
        <listitem>example</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Attributes</title>
        <listitem>language: required or implicit, reference to a controlled vocabulary</listitem>
        <listitem>text: required, non-empty string</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Children</title>
        <listitem>none</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para/>
    </section>

</section>
  <section id="module-collocations">
  <title>Collocations module</title>
  <para>
    This module makes it possible to organize the examples inside a sense into groups
    based on the headword's collocate.
  </para>
  <para>
    Note that this is basically just a mechanism for grouping examples.
    If implementors want to do more complicated things with collocations,
    such as giving them definition and translations,
    then they should treat them as separate (multiword) entries,
    and use the linking module to transclude them as subentries.
  </para>
  <para>
    TBD.
  </para>
</section>
  <section id="module-labelling">
  <title>Labelling module</title>
  <para>
    This module adds an element, of data type label, as an optional child to pretty much everything.
    For attaching pragmatic labels such as "vulgar", "colloquial", "regional"n.
  </para>
  <para>
    TBD.
  </para>
</section>
  <section id="module-linking">
  <title>Linking module</title>
  <para>
    Handles
    (1) synonyms, antonyms, cross-referencing,
    (2) variants,
    (3) subentrying and subsensing
  </para>
  <para>
    TBD.
  </para>
</section>
  <section id="module-scoping">
  <title>Scoping module</title>
  <para>
    Allows partOfSpeech, pronunciation, inflectedForm as children of sense.
    To make it possible top say that, for example,
    a headword has one plural form in one sense and another plural form in another sense.
  </para>
  <para>
    TBD.
  </para>
</section>
  <section id="module-controlled-vocabularies">
  <title>Controlled vocabularies module</title>
  <para>
    This module changes the definition of several attributes in several objects
    (such as partOfSpeech.value, inflectedForm.indicator, label.value)
    from free open string (= can take any text) to a reference to a controlled vocabulary.
  </para>
  <para>
    This module adds features to the lexicographicResource data type for specifying
    what those controlled vocabularies, either by listing them explicitely
    or by referring to external authority.
  </para>
  <para>
    The module makes it possible to model complex contraints on the values that
    the various attributes can take. For example, the partOfSpeech.value attribute
    takes different values depending on whether its parent is
    entry or headwordTranslation, and if headwordTranslation, depending on what
    the headwordTranslation's language is.
  </para>
  <para>
    TBD.
  </para>
</section>
</article>