<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../docbook/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED">
]>
<section id="csprd01">
<title>Tracking of changes in response to the 1st Public Review</title>
<para>This section tracks major changes made to this specification compared to the Committee
        Specification Draft 01 <ulink
            url="&previous-loc;/&name;-&pstage;.pdf"
            >&previous-loc;/&name;-&pstage;.pdf</ulink>.
        The initial Public Review took place from 22nd September 2023 until 17th November 2023.</para>
<orderedlist>
<!-- Add new change track items to the bottom of the list -->

<listitem><para>
Clarifications have been added to explain why DMLex allows lexicographic resources with zero entries and entries with zero senses, in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/52">52</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
The data type of <code>pronunciation.soundFile</code> has been changed to Internationalized Resource Identifier (IRI), in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/54">54</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the Controlled Values Module, the properties of various object types such as <code>forHeadwords</code>, <code>forPartOfSpeech</code> and so on, which had originally been intended to model various constraints on the use of tags, have been radically simplified into a single property called <code>for</code> – in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/55">55</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the Linking Module, uniqueness constraints on <code>relation</code> have been removed in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/56">56</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
The Etymology Module has been updated to disallow the existence of empty etymologies, in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/59">59</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the XML and JSON serializations (which are normative) and in the NVH serialization (which is informative), items which have <code>id</code> properties (those are: entries, senses, collocate markers) have been changed so that the <code>id</code> property is relevant only if implementing the Linking Module – in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/65">65</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the Linking Module, the <code>member_id</code> property of <code>member</code> has been changed to <code>ref</code> to avoid a potential misunderstanding about the purpose of this property, in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/66">66</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the Linking Module, the <code>obverseListingOrder</code> property of <code>member</code> has been made optional in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/67">67</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the Linking Module, the <code>role</code> property of <code>memberType</code> has been made optional in response to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/68">68</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the XML serialization, whitespace handling rules have been added, both at the default level for all elements, and specifically for elements which are allowed to contain inline markup, in reponse to a review comment (GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/69">69</ulink>).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Multiple changes have made to the Examples section to correct inconsistencies between the examples and the rest of the specificiation, in response to various review comments (including GitHub issue <ulink url="https://github.com/oasis-tcs/lexidma/issues/62">62</ulink>).  
</para></listitem>

<!-- Add new change track items to the bottom of the list
<listitem>
<para>[This is a suggested wording for your change track item:] In response to comment(s) nnn, nnn, and nnn, following changes have been made to
feature XYZ: [description of changes]... </para>
</listitem>
-->

</orderedlist>

</section>
