<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                         <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../docbook/xinclude.mod" >
                         %xinclude;
                         <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
]>

<section id="core">
  <title>DMLex Core</title>
  <para>The DMLex Core provides data types for modelling monolingual dictionaries (called <emphasis>lexicographic resources</emphasis> in DMLex) where headwords, definitions and examples are all in one and the same language. DMLex Core gives you the tools you need to model simple dictionary entries which consist of the following data types:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_lexicographicResource">lexicographicResource</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_entry">entry</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_partOfSpeech">partOfSpeech</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_inflectedForm">inflectedForm</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_sense">sense</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_definition">definition</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_label">label</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_pronunciation">pronunciation</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_transcription">transcription</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para><literal><olink targetptr="core_example">example</olink></literal></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section id="optionalroots">
    <title>Optional roots</title>
    <para>
      When exchanging data encoded in a DMLex serialization
      which has the concept of a "root" or top-level object, such as XML, JSON or NVH,
      the object types <literal>lexicographicResource</literal> and <literal>entry</literal>
      can serve as such roots.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="fragid">
    <title>Fragment identification</title>
    <para>
      Incomplete parts of DMLex objects represent valid fragments as long as it is possible to identify their complete source DMLex object.
      For a particular serialization, this can be achieved by:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Making sure the fragment contains all <olink targetptr="uniqueids">unique properties</olink> of the DMLex parent-child hierarchy that are necessary to determine its source object.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Using a serialization-specific addressing mechanism (e.g. XPath for XML, JMESPath for JSON or an NVH query) to provide the location of the fragment in the source DMLex object.</para>
        </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	  <section id="frag_iri">
		  <title>DMLex fragment identification strings</title>
		  <para>DMLex provides a recommended method for addressing DMLex objects present on-line, useful for linking (cf. <xref linkend="linking"/>) and general interoperability. Implementing this method is not <glossterm>required</glossterm> for conformance.</para>

		  <para>Every fragment <glossterm>should</glossterm> be assigned a unique fragment identification string, composed of <literal>lexicographicResource.uri</literal>, with protocol identification prefix (such as <literal>http://</literal> or <literal>https://</literal>) removed, and a sequence of identifiers that uniquely determines the path in the DMLex tree structure. The DMLex fragment identification string of the root object <literal>lexicographicResource</literal> is the value of its attribute <literal>lexicographicResource.uri</literal>, with protocol identification prefix (such as <literal>http://</literal> or <literal>https://</literal>) removed. The fragment identification strings of its direct children are constructed as follows:</para>

		<para><literal>lexicographicResource.uri/objectTypeName/objectID</literal></para>

		<para>(We define below how object IDs are created.)</para>

		<para>The DMLex fragment identification strings of descendant objects are constructed by appending the children's type names and IDs to the fragment identification strings of their direct parents, using “/” as the delimiter. In other words, the full template for a fragment identification string looks as follows:</para>

		<para><literal>lexicographicResource.uri/objectTypeName/objectID/child1TypeName/child1ID/child2TypeName/child2ID/…</literal></para>

		<para>For example, a particular <literal><olink targetptr="core_sense">sense</olink></literal> (which is a property of <literal><olink targetptr="core_entry">entry</olink></literal>) is assigned the following fragment identification string:</para>

		<para><literal>lexicographicResource.uri/entry/entryID/sense/senseID</literal></para>

		<para>A fragment identification string of an <literal><olink targetptr="core_example">example</olink></literal> (which is a property of <literal><olink targetptr="core_sense">sense</olink></literal>, which is a property of <literal><olink targetptr="core_entry">entry</olink></literal>) has the following structure:</para>

		<para><literal>lexicographicResource.uri/entry/entryID/sense/senseID/example/exampleID</literal></para>

		<section id="objectids">
			<title>Object IDs</title>

			<para>For the purpose of creating DMLex fragment identification strings, each object is assigned a unique ID relative to its parent, based on values of its properties declared as <glossterm>unique</glossterm>. Multiple situations can occur:</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>The object type has a single <glossterm>unique</glossterm> property with an arity of “exactly one”, and the value of the property is a string or a number. In this case, the object ID is the string or the number, with the following modifications performed in that particular order:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>every “\” (ASCII character 5C) is replaced by “\\”</listitem>
						<listitem>every “~” (ASCII character 7E) is replaced by “\~”</listitem>
						<listitem>every “_” (ASCII character 5F) is replaced by “\_”</listitem>
						<listitem>every “0” (zero, ASCII character 30) is replaced by “\0”</listitem>
						<listitem>all IRI-unsafe characters (outside the <literal>iunreserved</literal> class according to [<link linkend="bib_rfc3987">RFC 3987</link>]) are percent-encoded according to [<link linkend="bib_rfc3986">RFC 3986</link>]</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>The object type has a single <glossterm>unique</glossterm> property with an arity of “exactly one”, and the value of the property is a child DMLex object. In this case, the object ID is the same as the object ID of the child object. (Note: this case actually does not occur in the specification as such; we list it here to streamline the description of the following cases.)</listitem>
				<listitem>The object type has a single <glossterm>unique</glossterm> property with an arbitrary arity. In this case, all the partial single values or child object IDs are constructed according to the steps 1. and 2., and the resulting object ID is their concatenation using “_” (ASCII character 5F) as a separator. The order of the partial values is driven by the <literal>listingOrder</literal> of the respective objects. If this procedure returns an empty string (which can happen in case of <glossterm>unique</glossterm> attributes that allow the arity of zero), the string “0” (zero, ASCII character 30) is used instead of the empty string.</listitem>
				<listitem>The object type has multiple <glossterm>unique</glossterm> properties. In this case, all the partial values or child object IDs are constructed according to the steps 1., 2. and 3., and the resulting object ID is their concatenation using “~” (ASCII character 5F) as a separator. The order of the partial values is driven by the order of the properties as given in this specification. (Note: all atributes marked as <glossterm>unique</glossterm> need to be represented in the ID, as empty values are replaced by “0” according to step 3. No empty IDs are allowed.)</listitem>
				<listitem>In specific situations it may happen there are multiple different objects with all the <glossterm>unique</glossterm> properties empty, i.e. multiple objects with duplicate IDs (the same sequence of zeros) emerge as the result of the step 4. One example of such a situation is multiple senses without <literal>indicator</literal>s or <literal>definition</literal>s, but with different translations. In that case, and only in that case, the value of <literal>listingOrder</literal> is concatenated to the sequence of zeros, to distinguish between the duplicate IDs. If there is only one such object, <literal>listingOrder</literal> is not concatenated to the sequence of zeros.</listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<para>DMLex does not define the structure of DMLex fragment identification strings for object types without <glossterm>unique</glossterm> properties.</para>
		</section>
		<section id="iri_examples">
			<title>DMLex fragment identification string examples</title>
			<para>Particular examples of DMLex fragment identification strings can then look as follows:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><literal>www.example.com/lexicon/entry/cat~1~noun</literal></listitem>
				<listitem><literal>www.example.com/lexicon/entry/cat~1~noun/sense/0~small%20furry%20animal</literal> (Here we assume that the sense's <literal>indicator</literal> is empty and it has one <literal>definition</literal> which says “small furry animal”).</listitem>
				<listitem><literal>www.example.com/lexicon/entry/cat~1~noun/sense/0~small%20furry%20animal/example/I%20have%20two%20dogs%20and%20a%20cat.</literal></listitem>
				<listitem><literal>www.example.com/lexicon/entry/cat~1~noun/sense/0~0</literal> (Here we assume that both the sense's <literal>definition</literal> and its <literal>indicator</literal> are empty, and there is only one such sense.)</listitem>
				<listitem><literal>www.example.com/lexicon/entry/cat~1~noun/sense/0~02</literal> (Here we assume that both the sense's <literal>definition</literal> and its <literal>indicator</literal> are empty, there are multiple such senses, and this is the sense number 2, of all this entry's senses.)</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	  </section>
  </section>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/lexicographicResource.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/entry.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/partOfSpeech.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/inflectedForm.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/sense.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/definition.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/label.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/pronunciation.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/transcription.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  <xi:include href="objectTypes/example.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</section>
