<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                         <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../docbook/xinclude.mod" >
                         %xinclude;
                         <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
]>

<section>

  <title>
    <code>label</code>
  </title>
  <para>Represents a restriction on its parent such as temporal (old-fashioned, neologism), regional (dialect), register (formal, colloquial), domain (medicine, politics) or grammar (singular-only).</para>
  <programlisting>
label: &lt;string&gt;
    listingOrder: (1..1) &lt;number&gt;
</programlisting>
  <section>
    <title>XML</title>
    <programlisting>
&lt;label value="..."/&gt;
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>JSON</title>
    <programlisting>
"..."
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
      <title>RDF</title>
      <programlisting>
&lt;entry&gt; dmlex:label [
  a dmlex:Label ;
  rdf:value "..." ;
  dmlex:listingOrder 1 ] .
      </programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>SQL</title>
    <programlisting>
create table labels (
    entryID int foreign key references entries(id),
    senseID int foreign key references senses(id),
    inflectedFormID int foreign key references inflectedForms(id),
    pronunciationID int foreign key references pronunciations(id),
    exampleID int foreign key references examples(id),
    value varchar(10),
    listingOrder int,
    id int primary key
)
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Comments</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The value of the label object is an abbreviation, a code or some other string of text which identifies the label, for example <code>neo</code> for neologism,  <code>colloq</code> for colloquial, <code>polit</code> for politics. You can use the <code>tag</code> datatype to explain the meaning of the label tags, to constrain which label tags are allowed to occur in your lexicographic resource, and to map them onto external inventories and ontologies.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <code>listingOrder</code> is the position of this label among other labels of the same entry. This can be implicit from the serialization.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A label applies to the object that it is a child of. When the label is a child of <code>entry</code>, then it applies to the headword in all its senses. When the label is a child of <code>sense</code>, then it applies to the headword in that sense only (<emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> including any subsenses linked to it using the Linking Module). When the label is a child of <code>inlectedForm</code>, then it applies only to that inflected form of the headword (in all senses). When the label is a child of <code>pronunciation</code>, then it applies only to that pronuciation of the headword (in all senses).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</section>
