<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                         <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../docbook/xinclude.mod" >
                         %xinclude;
                         <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
]>

<section id="core_lexicographicResource">
  <title>
    <code>lexicographicResource</code>
  </title>
  <para>Represents a dictionary. A lexicographic resource is a dataset which can be used, viewed and
    read by humans as a dictionary and – simultaneously – ingested, processed and understood by
    software agents as a machine-readable dataset.</para>
  
  <note>
    <para>The correct name of this data type in
      DMLex is <emphasis>lexicographic</emphasis>, not <emphasis>lexical</emphasis>, resource.</para>
  </note>

  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Properties</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal>title</literal>
        <glossterm>optional</glossterm> (zero or one). Non-empty string. A human-readable title of
        the lexicographic resource.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal>uri</literal>
        <glossterm>required</glossterm> (zero or one). The URI of the lexicographic resource,
        identifying it on the Web.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal>langCode</literal>
        <glossterm>required</glossterm> (exactly one). The IETF language code of the language that
        this lexicographic resource describes.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal><olink targetptr="core_entry">entry</olink></literal>
        <glossterm>optional</glossterm> (zero or more)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Comments</title>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <code>langCode</code> identifies the language of headwords, definitions and examples in this
        dictionary. DMLex is based on the assumption that all headwords in a lexicographic resource
        are in the same language, and that definitions and examples, if any are included in the
        lexicographic resource, are in that language too. The <code>langCode</code> property of
          <code>lexicographicResource</code> informs potential users of the lexicographic resource
        which language that is.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Ideally, a lexicographic resource should include at least one entry. However, DMLex
        specifies that <code>entry</code> is optional in <code>lexicographicResource</code> to allow
        for the existence of lexicographic resources which are not yet complete. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The <code>lexicographicResource</code> data type does not prescribe properties for
	  detailed metadata about the lexicographic resource, implementers are advised to refer to
	  the properties in the <link linkend="DublinCore">Dublin Core <code>elements</code> namespace</link> as for basic metadata. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>DMLex allows lexicographic resources to contain zero entries. This is to enable the
        existence of lexicographic resources which are work in progress, and lexicographic resources
        whose only purpose is to contain relations (defined in the <olink targetptr="linking">DMLex Linking Module</olink>)
        that link entries from other lexicographic resources.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <example>
    <title>XML</title>
    <programlisting>
&lt;lexicographicResource uri="..." langCode="..."&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;...&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;entry.../&gt;
&lt;/lexicographicResource&gt;
    </programlisting>
  </example>

  <example>
    <title>JSON</title>
    <programlisting>
{
    "title": "...",
    "langCode": "...",
    "entries": [...]
}
</programlisting>
  </example>

  <example>
    <title>RDF</title>
    <programlisting>
@prefix dmlex: &lt;http://www.oasis-open.org/to-be-confirmed/dmlex&gt; .

&lt;#id&gt; a dmlex:LexicographicResource ;
  dmlex:title "..." ;
  dmlex:uri "..." ;
  dmlex:langCode "..." ;
  dmlex:entry &lt;entry1&gt; , ... .
      </programlisting>
  </example>

  <example>
    <title>Relational database</title>
    <graphic fileref="core/databaseDiagrams/lexicographicResource.svg" contentwidth="16cm"/>
  </example>

</section>
