<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                         <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../docbook/xinclude.mod" >
                         %xinclude;
                         <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
]>

<section id="core_lexicographicResource">
  <title>
    <code>lexicographicResource</code>
  </title>
  <para>Represents a dictionary. A lexicographic resource is a dataset which can be used, viewed and
    read by humans as a dictionary and – simultaneously – ingested, processed and understood by
    software agents as a machine-readable database.</para>
  
  <note>
    <para>The correct name of this data type in
      DMLex is <emphasis>lexicographic</emphasis>, not <emphasis>lexical</emphasis>, resource.</para>
  </note>

  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Contents</title>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal>title</literal>
        <glossterm>optional</glossterm> (zero or one). Non-empty string. A human-readable title of
        the lexicographic resource.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal>uri</literal>
        <glossterm>optional</glossterm> (zero or one). The URI of the lexicographic resource,
        identifying it on the Web.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal>language</literal>
        <glossterm>required</glossterm> (exactly one). The IETF language code of the language that
        this lexicographic resource describes.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><literal><olink targetptr="core_entry">entry</olink></literal>
        <glossterm>optional</glossterm> (zero, one or more)
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Comments</title>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <code>language</code> identifies the language of headwords, definitions and examples in this
        dictionary. DMLex is based on the assumption that all headwords in a lexicographic resource
        are in the same language, and that definitions and examples, if any occur in the
        lexicographic resource, are in that language too. The <code>language</code> child object of
          <code>lexicographicResource</code> informs potential users of the lexicographic resource
        which language that is.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The main role of a lexicographic resource is to contain entries (<code>entry</code>
        objects). The other object type that can optionally occur inside a
          <code>lexicographicResource</code>, <code>tag</code>, is for lists of look-up values such
        as part-of-speech labels.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Ideally, a lexicograpphic resouce should include at least one entry. However, DMLex specifies that
      <code>entry</code> is optional in <code>lexicographicResouce</code> to allow for the existence of
      lexicographic resouces which are not yet complete.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The <code>lexicographicResource</code> data type does not contain fields for detailed metadata
      about the lexicographic resource, such as author, editor, publisher, copyright status or publication year.
      Describing these properties of lexicographic resources is outside the scope of DMLex. DMLex is a formalism
      for modelling the internal structure of a lexicographic resource, not its metadata.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <example>
    <title>XML</title>
    <programlisting>
&lt;lexicographicResource uri="..." language="..."&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;...&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;entry.../&gt;
    &lt;tag.../&gt;
&lt;/lexicographicResource&gt;
    </programlisting>
  </example>

  <example>
    <title>JSON</title>
    <programlisting>
{
    "title": "...",
    "language": "...",
    "entries": [...],
    "tags": [...]
}
</programlisting>
  </example>

  <example>
    <title>RDF</title>
    <programlisting>
@prefix dmlex: &lt;http://www.oasis-open.org/to-be-confirmed/dmlex&gt; .

&lt;#id&gt; a dmlex:LexicographicResource ;
  dmlex:title "..." ;
  dmlex:uri "..." ;
  dmlex:language "..." ;
  dmlex:entry &lt;entry1&gt; , ... ;
  dmlex:tag ... .
      </programlisting>
  </example>

  <example>
    <title>Relational database</title>
    <graphic fileref="core/databaseDiagrams/lexicographicResource.svg" contentwidth="16cm"/>
  </example>

</section>
