<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
                         <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../docbook/xinclude.mod" >
                         %xinclude;
                         <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
]>

<section id="core_sense">

  <title>
    <code>sense</code>
  </title>
  <para>Represents one of possibly many meanings (or meaning potentials) of the headword.</para>
  <programlisting>
sense: &lt;id&gt;
    listingOrder: (1..1) &lt;number&gt;
    indicator: (0..1) &lt;string&gt;
    label: (0..n)
    definition: (0..n)
    example: (0..n)
</programlisting>
  <section>
    <title>XML</title>
    <programlisting>
&lt;sense id="..."&gt;
    &lt;indicator&gt;...&lt;/indicator&gt;
    &lt;label.../&gt;
    &lt;definition.../&gt;
    &lt;example.../&gt;
&lt;/sense&gt;
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>JSON</title>
    <programlisting>
{
    "id": "...",
    "indicator": "...",
    "labels": [...],
    "definitions": [...],
    "examples": [...]
}
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
      <title>RDF</title>
      <programlisting>
&lt;id&gt; a dmlex:Sense ;
  dmlex:listingOrder 1 ;
  dmlex:indicator "..." ;
  dmlex:label ... ;
  dmlex:definition ... ;
  dmlex:example ... .
      </programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>SQL</title>
    <programlisting>
create table senses (
    entryID int foreign key references entries(id),
    id int primary key,
    indicator nvarchar(50),
    listingOrder int
)
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Comments</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <code>listingOrder</code> represents the position of this sense among other senses of the same entry. Can be implicit from the serialization.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <code>indicator</code> is a short statement, in the same language as the headword, that gives an indication of the meaning of a sense and permits its differentiation from other senses in the entry. Indicators are sometimes used in dictionaries instead of or in addition to definitions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <code>definition</code> is a statement, in the same language as the headword, that describes and/or explains the meaning of a sense. In DMLex, the term definition encompasses not only formal definitions, but also less formal explanations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Note</title>
    <para>An <emphasis role="strong">entry</emphasis> is a container for formal properties of the headword such as orthography, morphology, syntax and pronunciation. A <emphasis role="strong">sense</emphasis> is a container for statements about the headword's semantics. DMLex deliberately makes it impossible to include morphological information at sense level. If you have an entry where each sense has slightly different morphological properties (eg. a noun has a weak plural in one sense and a strong plural in another) then, in DMLex, you need to treat it as two entries (homographs), and you can use the Linking Module two link the two entries together and to make sure they are always shown together to human users.</para>
  </section>
  

</section>
